<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Catalogue of Latin Manuscripts in the John Rylands Library</title>
                <funder/>
                <principal>John Hodgson</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Cataloguer</resp>
                    <name>Joanne Edge</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The University of Manchester Library</publisher>
                <date calendar="Gregorian">2018</date>
                <pubPlace>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>The John Rylands Library</addrLine>
                        <street>150 Deansgate</street>
                        <settlement>Manchester</settlement>
                        <postCode>M3 3EH</postCode>
                        <addrLine><ref
                                target="http://www.library.manchester.ac.uk/specialcollections/">The
                                John Rylands Library </ref></addrLine>
                        <addrLine><email>uml.special-collections@manchester.ac.uk</email></addrLine>
                    </address>
                </pubPlace>
                <idno>UkMaJRU-Latin-MS-98</idno>
                <availability xml:id="displayImageRights" status="restricted">
                    <p>Zooming image © University of Manchester Library, All rights reserved.</p>
                </availability>
                <availability xml:id="downloadImageRights" status="restricted">
                    <licence>Images made available for download are licensed under a Creative
                        Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License (CC BY-NC
                        3.0)</licence>
                </availability>
                <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
                    <licence>This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons
                        Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="UkMaJRU-Latin-MS-98"
                    xml:lang="eng">

                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>United Kingdom</country>
                        <region type="county">Greater Manchester</region>
                        <settlement>Manchester</settlement>
                        <institution>The University of Manchester Library</institution>
                        <repository>The John Rylands Library</repository>
                        <collection>Latin Manuscripts</collection>

                        <idno>Latin MS 98</idno>

                        <msName>The Ottonian Gospels.</msName>

                    </msIdentifier>

                    <msContents>
                        <summary>Gospel Book, produced for Otto III between 996-1002, possibly by
                            the Trier artist known as the 'Master of the Registrum Gregorii'. It
                            seems to have been in Cologne soon after it was completed and influenced
                            the decoration of a number of manuscripts executed there in the early
                            11th century, which provide a good idea of the miniatures it now
                            lacks.</summary>

                        <msItem n="1">

                            <locus from="1r" to="3v">1r-3v</locus>
                            <title>Epistula ad Damasum</title>
                            <author>
                                <name type="person" subtype="aut"
                                    ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/95147024">
                                    <persName type="standard" xml:lang="eng">Jerome, Saint,
                                        347-420</persName><persName type="display">Saint Jerome (b.
                                        347, d. 420, theologian and priest</persName>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin</textLang>

                        </msItem>

                        <msItem n="2">

                            <locus from="4r" to="61r">4r-61r</locus>
                            <title>Book of Matthew</title>
                            <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin</textLang>

                        </msItem>

                        <msItem n="3">

                            <locus from="62r" to="92v">62r-92v</locus>
                            <title>Book of Mark</title>
                            <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin</textLang>

                        </msItem>

                        <msItem n="4">

                            <locus from="93v" to="149r">93v-149r</locus>
                            <title>Book of Luke</title>
                            <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin</textLang>

                        </msItem>

                        <msItem n="5">

                            <locus from="150v" to="192r">150v-192r</locus>
                            <title>Book of John</title>
                            <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin</textLang>

                        </msItem>

                        <msItem n="6">

                            <locus from="192r" to="201v">192r-201v</locus>
                            <title>Capitulare evangeliorum</title>
                            <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin</textLang>

                        </msItem>

                        <msItem n="7">

                            <locus from="202r" to="203r">202r-203r</locus>
                            <title>Common of Saints</title>
                            <textLang mainLang="lat">Latin</textLang>

                        </msItem>

                    </msContents>

                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc form="codex">
                            <supportDesc material="parchment">
                                <support><material>Parchment</material>.</support>

                                <extent>
                                    <measure unit="leaf" n="207">ff. 207 (ii+205)</measure>
                                    <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                                        <height quantity="240">240</height>
                                        <width quantity="193">193</width>
                                    </dimensions>
                                </extent>

                                <foliation>
                                    <p>Foliated 1-205.</p>
                                </foliation>

                                <collation>
                                    <list>
                                        <item>Quire 1<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></item>
                                        <item>Quire A<hi rend="superscript">8</hi></item>
                                        <item>Quire B<hi rend="superscript">6</hi></item>
                                        <item>Quire C<hi rend="superscript">4</hi>, 1 and 2 cut
                                            out</item>
                                        <item>Quires D-H<hi rend="superscript">8</hi></item>
                                        <item>Quire I<hi rend="superscript">6</hi></item>
                                        <item>Quire K absent</item>
                                        <item>Quire L<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></item>
                                        <item>Quires M-P<hi rend="superscript">8</hi></item>
                                        <item>Quire Q<hi rend="superscript">?4</hi>, 1-3 cut
                                            out</item>
                                        <item>Quires R-Z<hi rend="superscript">8</hi></item>
                                        <item>Quire aa absent</item>
                                        <item>Quire bb<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></item>
                                        <item>Quires cc-ff<hi rend="superscript">8</hi></item>
                                        <item>Quire gg<hi rend="superscript">6</hi></item>
                                        <item>Quire hh<hi rend="superscript">8</hi></item>
                                        <item>Quire ii<hi rend="superscript">4</hi></item>
                                    </list>
                                </collation>

                                <condition>
                                    <p>In very good condition, although some frontispieces to the
                                        Gospels have been cut out.</p>
                                </condition>
                            </supportDesc>

                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout columns="1" writtenLines="25">
                                    <p>1 column, 25 lines to a page</p>
                                </layout>
                            </layoutDesc>

                        </objectDesc>

                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote scope="major" script="miniscule">
                                <desc>Written in <term>miniscule</term> by a single scribe</desc>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>

                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote>
                                <p>This manuscript is now generally assigned to the outstanding
                                    Trier artist of the Ottonian period known as the &apos;Master of
                                    the Registrum Gregorii&apos;. Brigitte Nitschke has doubted this
                                    (see her Die Handschrijtengruppe urn den Meister des Registrum
                                    Gregorii (Münstersche Studien zur Kunstgeschichte, Bd.v (1966)),
                                    particularly pp. 72-74, 81). For a detailed discussion of the
                                    whole matter see Peter Bloch and Hermann Schnitzler, Die
                                    ottonische Kölner Malerschule, 2 vols. (Düsseldorf, 1970) and
                                    the references there, particularly the notes in Bd.II, pp. 15,
                                    17-21. Bloch and Schnitzler devote a whole section to this
                                    manuscript under the heading &apos;Das Evangeliar des Trierer
                                    Gregormeisters in Manchester, John Rylands Library Cod. 98&apos;
                                    (Bd. II, pp. 15-21) giving (a) a full collation (II.16-17), (b)
                                    a reconstruction of its imperfections from the Stuttgart Gospels
                                    (Landesbibliothek MS. Bibl. f. 21), a MS. which was copied from
                                    it (II.15), (c) notes on its provenance (II.17), localisation
                                    and dating (II.17-19) and style (II.19-20), and (d) an account
                                    of its significance (II.20-21). They date it, &apos;with great
                                    probability&apos;, to between 996 and 1002. It apparently found
                                    its way to Cologne soon after it was completed and influenced
                                    the decoration of a number of manucsripts executed there in the
                                    early 11th century. From these we may obtain a good idea of the
                                    miniatures it now lacks.</p></decoNote>
                            <decoNote type="illustration">
                                <p>Folio <locus from="1r" to="1r">1r</locus>: Outer frame gold,
                                    edged with red; four small leaves in gold at the angles. Inner
                                    frame of three main bands, separated by red lines. The outermost
                                    and broadest is of acanthus-foliage, in white on dark blue: the
                                    next, narrow, plain gold: the innermost, gold scroll-work on
                                    light purple. At the angles, four squares of light red, with a
                                    conventional four-petalled flower in white and gold. The main
                                    ground purple, with some small ornaments in white: mainly
                                    occupied by a large B, of minuscule form, of gold edged with red
                                    (as throughout), containing panels of white and green. It has
                                    knots of plaited work and a dragon&apos;s head. Within it the
                                    ground is a brilliant green, with white ornaments, in which is
                                    set a large knot of plaited work. Around this latter are the
                                    letters: E, A, Ti, S (Beatis-) in gold - some filled with green.
                                    Below, two lines of gold uncials: -simo papae Damaso Hieronimus.
                                    Old uncoloured silk guard.</p>
                                <p>Folio <locus from="10r" to="10r">10r</locus>: Eusebian canons.
                                    The section numbers are arranged in four or three columns on a
                                    page. They are in red at first, then in black. Short gold lines
                                    separate the groups of numbers. The framework is in the form of
                                    the façade of a classical temple: pediment, with acroteria (on
                                    the gable only, except on the first page); architrave (inscribed
                                    with the title of the Canon, e.g. Canon primus in quo iiii. Mat.
                                    Mar. Luc. Ioh., in gold uncials: round-headed arches underneath.
                                    The columns supporting these arches are very variously coloured
                                    and patterned. On the first page there are five columns treated
                                    thus (from left): nos. 1 and 5 are pink, with spiral wavy lines,
                                    alternately gold and white: nos. 2 and 4 are green, with
                                    irregular patches of gold: no. 3 is plain gold. The capitals are
                                    of conventional foliage, usually in pink or blue (or both),
                                    heightened with white. The bases uniformly gold. The colours of
                                    pediment, architrave, etc., are varied: pink, purple, blues, and
                                    greens</p>
                                <p>Folio <locus from="16r">16r</locus>: Frontispiece to Matthew.
                                    Outer frame vermilion, edged with blue and patterned with gold:
                                    projections of gold foliage at the angles and in the centres of
                                    the sides. Inner frame mainly gold, with red lines and small
                                    patterns in colour: at the angles, dark blue acanthus, with
                                    white patterns. In the centre of each side is a medallion with
                                    gold ground set on a square of dull blue, with groups of three
                                    white dots in the spandrels. Each medallion contains a bust, in
                                    colour, of a beardless man in mantle, fastened on the right
                                    shoulder. The mantle is twice pink and twice green, over white.
                                    Each medallion is edged with a red line dotted with white. The
                                    heads of the busts at top and on left look to the right. The
                                    others look to the left. Each has an inscription in tiny
                                    capitals round the head, as follows: 1 (top): ROMANE. R. P. DlVI
                                    MEM OTTO IMPER. AVG. 2 (left): XPIANE RELIGIONIS ET ROMANE R. P.
                                    OTTO IMP. AVG. 3 (bottom): D. CORONATVS ROMANE R. P. OTTO IMPER.
                                    AVG. 4 (right): XPIANE RELIGIONIS ET ROMANE. R. P. OTTO IMP.
                                    Main ground purple: within the convolutions of the foliage it is
                                    green, with white dots. It is occupied by a large gold L and I
                                    (the latter springing into foliage). These have panels of white
                                    plaited-work about them, and below them, in gold uncials, the
                                    letters: -ber generationis.</p>
                                <p>Folios <locus from="11v" to="11v">11v</locus> and <locus
                                        from="17r" to="17r">17r</locus>: framed in green and gold,
                                    and the text of the genealogy is written in gold as far as i.
                                    27: qui uocatur christus. Initials of chapters are in plain
                                    gold: others in red.</p>
                                <p>Folio <locus from="62r" to="62r">62r</locus>: five bands, three
                                    of purple and two of green. On these, in gold capitals: Incipit
                                    ar/gumentum /Evangelii / secundum/ Marcum. Marcus euangelista
                                    dei. Fine gold initial. On a patch of purple, in gold uncials:
                                    Expl. argumentum. hic. capitula sequentis</p>
                                <p>Folio <locus from="64v" to="65r">64v-65r</locus>: Framed
                                    decorations. On f. 64v the main ground is green. On it are four
                                    bands of purple, inscribed in gold capitals: Incipit li/ber sci
                                    evan/gelii secun/dum Marcum. On f. 65r the main ground is
                                    purple: occupied by a large gold foliated I and the letters
                                    NITIVM. The frame contains plaited work in gold on green.</p>
                                <p>Folio <locus from="98r" to="98r">98r</locus>: Full-page
                                    decoration. Outer frame vermilion. Then two bands of gold and a
                                    band of white between them, with gold plaited-work. Within this,
                                    several bands of wavy lines-white, gold, purple. In the centres
                                    of the sides of the frame are set four squares, framed in green,
                                    containing rosettes (2) and crossshaped ornaments (2), mainly in
                                    red and purple. Ground of panel, purple. A large Q occupies most
                                    of it, which is in gold, with panels of green and white. Below
                                    it, in gold uncials: -uoniam quidem.</p>
                                <p>Folio <locus from="150v" to="150v">150v</locus>: Title to John:
                                    Incipit ar/gumentum/ evangelii/ secundum/Iohannem /, in gold
                                    capitals, on alternate bands of purple and green Prologue: Hic
                                    est Johannes. Gold initial. In gold uncials on purple: Expl.
                                    argumentum.</p>
                                <p>Folio <locus from="153v" to="153v">153v</locus>: Full-page. Frame
                                    in gold, and purple with gold plaited-work. Ground within, green
                                    with four bands of purple (as for Mark), inscribed in gold
                                    capitals: Incipit liber / sci evange/lii secundum/Iohannem. At
                                    the angles are four small square pictutes, with light purple
                                    ground, each representing a black-haired beardless Evangelist,
                                    seated. Each has a sloping desk on a shaft, with a ledge to
                                    support the book. Top left: Dark mantle over bluish white.
                                    Bending forward, he writes in a book on his knee: no book on
                                    desk on right. Top right: Pink mantle over bluish white. Desk on
                                    left. He sits, holding a pen, supporting a book on his left
                                    knee, and looking to right. Bottom left: pink mantle over bluish
                                    white. Leans forward to right, left hand to his face, right
                                    elbow on knee, finger pointing to desk with book on right.
                                    Bottom right: dark mantle over bluish white. Desk on left with
                                    book. He sits, leaning his face on his right hand and looking
                                    towards the desk. The classical feeling in these small pictures
                                    is very strong.</p>
                                <p>Folio <locus from="154r" to="154r">154r</locus>: Full-page. Frame
                                    gold, blue acanthus pattern, gold, green. Inner ground purple,
                                    occupied by the letters I over N in gold, with panels of white
                                    plaited-work and gold foliage. Above and below, in gold uncials:
                                    principio erat uerbum. Five small square pictures, with purple
                                    frames and gold grounds, set in the centres of the sides and
                                    centre of the page, represent: centre, The Lamb, with
                                    cross-nimbus, facing right, his breast pierced by a spear.
                                    Bottom, half-length angel in pink over blue, and blue-white
                                    wings, looking up to right and holding up scroll over left hand.
                                    Right, pink lion, with blue wings, couchant, head to right, a
                                    book between his fore-feet. Left, winged ox, similar, head to
                                    left. Top, eagle, with blue wings and pink body, looking back to
                                    right, a roll under his right claw.</p>
                                <p>Folio <locus from="192r" to="192r">192r</locus>: in gold uncials
                                    on purple: Inc. breuiarium/Lectionum euangeli/orum legendorum
                                    per / circirculum (sic) anni. Rubric. In uigilia natalis domini
                                    hora nona ad sanctam mariam.</p>
                            </decoNote>

                        </decoDesc>

                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding notBefore="1500" notAfter="1600">
                                <p>Brown leather, with plain central panel and roll-pattern, over
                                    wooden boards, two metal clasps with slight ornament.</p>
                                <p>16th century</p>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                    </physDesc>

                    <history>
                        <origin><p><origPlace><country ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/316400406"
                                        >Germany</country><placeName
                                        ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/135701727" cert="low"
                                        >Trier</placeName></origPlace>
                                <origDate calendar="Gregorian" notBefore="0996" notAfter="1002"
                                    >996-1002 CE</origDate>
                            </p>
                        </origin>

                        <provenance>
                            <p>In Cologne soon after creation, as it influenced a number of
                                manuscripts that were illuminated there in the early 11th
                                century</p>
                            <p>Purchased by <name type="person" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9985420"
                                    subtype="fmo">
                                    <persName type="display">James Ludovic Lindsay (b. 1847, d.
                                        1913), 26th Earl of Crawford</persName><persName
                                        type="standard">Lindsay, James Ludovic,
                                    1847-1913</persName></name> at the Fountaine Sale in <date
                                    when="1894">1894</date> (CLL, Oct.-Dec. 1895 [sic], no. 759).
                                Crawford&apos;s librarian, Mr. Edmond, visited the Bollandists
                                    in<date when="1895-10"> October 1895</date> to try to discover
                                further details about it, but, he reported, &apos;all in vain&apos;,
                                although <name type="person" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/88889398">
                                    <persName type="display">Joseph van den Gheyn (b. 1854, d.
                                        1913), monk and Bollandist</persName><persName
                                        type="standard">van den Gheyn, Joseph,
                                    1854-1913</persName></name> &apos;spent hours with me hunting
                                for information&apos; (ibid. no. 712). It must, he informed Lord
                                Crawford, have been acquired by them after the French Revolution,
                                but &apos;unfortunately they have no register of gifts, or letter
                                book in which such a gift might be recorded&apos; (ibid. nos.
                                712-13).</p>
                            <p>On the fore-edge of the manuscript, in black ink, is written
                                &apos;Biblia&apos; and that the watermark (fleur-de-lys) on the
                                front fly-leaf approximates to Heawood, nos. 1673, 1679 (Dutch,
                                1690s).</p>
                        </provenance>

                        <acquisition>
                            <p>Purchased by Enriqueta Rylands in <date calendar="#Gregorian"
                                    when="1901">1901</date> from <name type="person"
                                    ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/9985420" subtype="fmo">
                                    <persName type="display">James Ludovic Lindsay (b. 1847, d.
                                        1913), 26th Earl of Crawford</persName><persName
                                        type="standard">Lindsay, James Ludovic,
                                    1847-1913</persName></name>. Bequeathed by Rylands to the John
                                Rylands Library in 1908.</p>
                        </acquisition>

                    </history>

                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source>Description based on <persName>M.R. James</persName>,
                                        <title>A Descriptive Catalogue of the Latin Manuscripts in
                                        the John Rylands Library at Manchester</title> (Manchester,
                                    1921), reprinted with an introduction and additional notes and
                                    corrections by F. Taylor (München, 1980), revised and expanded
                                    by Joanne Edge.</source>
                            </recordHist>

                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>The manuscript is available for consultation by any accredited
                                    reader.</p>
                            </availability>
                            <note/>
                        </adminInfo>

                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl><ref target="https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/829885323">Brigitte
                                    Nitschke, Die Handschriftengruppe um den Meister des Registrum
                                    Gregorii (Milnstersche Studien zur Kunstgeschichte, Bd.v
                                    (Recklinghausen: Verlag Aurel Bongers, 1966).</ref></bibl>
                            <bibl><ref target="https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/504167916">Peter Bloch
                                    and Hermann Schnitzler, Die ottonische Kölner Malerschule, 2
                                    vols. (Düsseldorf, 1970).</ref></bibl>
                            <bibl><ref target="https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/888261759">Carl
                                    Nordenfalk, The chronology of the Registrum Master in
                                    Kunsthistorische Forschungen Otto Pücht zu Ehren zu seinem 70.
                                    Geburtstag, ed. Artur Rosenauer und Gerold Weber, pp. 62-76
                                    (Salzburg: Residenz Verl, 1972).</ref></bibl>
                            <bibl><ref target="https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1723816">Carl
                                    Nordenfalk, &apos;Ottonian Illumination&apos; in A. Grabar and
                                    C. Nordenfalk, Early Medieval Painting (New York: SKIRA, 1967),
                                    pp. 202-203.</ref></bibl>
                            <bibl><ref target="https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/248011980">Florentine
                                    Mütherich, Das Evangeliar Ottos III: Clm 4453 der Bayerischen
                                    Staatsbibliothek München (Darmstadt: Wiss. Buchges,
                                2001).</ref></bibl>
                            <bibl><ref target="https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/802831528">J. J. G.
                                    Alexander, The Decorated Letter (London: Thames and Hudson,
                                    1978).</ref></bibl>
                            <bibl><ref target="https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/888224249">Meyer
                                    Schapiro, The Parma Ildefonsus (MS 1650 in the Palatine Library
                                    of Parma ... the treatise of Ildefonsus, bishop of Toledo ... on
                                    the virginity of Mary.) A Romanesque illuminated manuscript from
                                    Cluny and related works (Providence, RI: Archaeological
                                    Institute of America, 1964).</ref></bibl>
                            <bibl><ref target="https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/400616">W. H. Frere,
                                    Bibliotheca musico-liturgica. A descriptive handlist of the
                                    musical and Latin-liturgical MSS. of the Middle Ages preserved
                                    in the libraries of Great Britain and Ireland (Plainsong and
                                    Mediaeval Music Society (Hildesheim, Gg. Olms, 1967), vol
                                    2.</ref></bibl>
                            <bibl><ref target="https://www.worldcat.org/oclc/471768617">E. A. Lowe,
                                    Palaeographical papers, 1907-1965 ed. Ludwig Bieler. (Oxford,
                                    the Clarendon Press, 1972).</ref></bibl>
                        </listBibl>

                    </additional>

                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
                    <bibl><ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/about.html#lcsh">Library of
                            Congress Subject Headings</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
                    <list>
                        <item><ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112549"
                            />Religion</item>
                        <item><ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85025219"
                                >Christianity</ref></item>
                        <item><ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88004788">Bible.
                                Latin--Versions--Vulgate</ref></item>
                        <item><ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96011928">Bible.
                                New Testament</ref></item>
                    </list>

                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>

        <revisionDesc>

            <change when="2018-10-16">
                <persName/>Joanne Edge</change>
            <change when="2019-08-02">
                <persName/>Joanne Edge</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<facsimile><!-- SAMPLE -->
<graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait" url="MS-HEBREW-GASTER-00086-000-00268.jp2"/>
<surface xml:id="i1">
<graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="portrait" height="6500px" width="5444px" url="MS-HEBREW-GASTER-00086-000-00268.jp2"/>
</surface><surface xml:id="i602">
<graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" rend="landscape" height="2224px" width="6500px" url="MS-HEBREW-GASTER-00086-000-00869.jp2"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
   <text><!-- SAMPLE -->
<body>
<div>
<pb n="Front board" xml:id="pb-Frontboard" facs="#i1"/>
<pb n="Front paste-down" xml:id="pb-Frontpaste-down" facs="#i2"/>
<pb n="ia" xml:id="pb-ia" facs="#i3"/>
<pb n="spine" xml:id="pb-spine" facs="#i599"/>
<pb n="top" xml:id="pb-top" facs="#i600"/>
<pb n="edge" xml:id="pb-edge" facs="#i601"/>
<pb n="bottom" xml:id="pb-bottom" facs="#i602"/>
</div></body>
    </text>
</TEI>
